Today's דף daf is
נא, Nun Aleph, fifty-one. We start about ten lines down on נא
עמוד א Nun Aleph Amud Aleph at the two dots, אם אינו
מכירה או
שאינו בקי.
Im eino makiro o she'eino
baki. So we have been talking about somebody who finds
himself outside of the city right before it gets dark on שבת,
Shabbos, and they are four thousand אמות amos away from their home,
but there's a tree exactly midpoint, so they can designate that tree
to be where they're starting שבת, Shabbos, and then they can get
from where they are to the tree, two thousand אמות, amos, and
from the tree to the home, two thousand אמות. amos. But it
says that if he doesn't recognize a tree and isn't aware of
any specific spot to designate, then at least give yourself two thousand
אמות amos from where you are and say you're starting שבת Shabbos
from where you are, and that at least you won't get home,
but you'll at least have two thousand אמות. amos. תוספות Tosafos points
out that when you're starting where you are, you don't really have
to say anything; as long as you don't do anything to undermine
it, you don't say anything in the opposite, you will effectively begin
שבת Shabbos where you are.
Yes, so if he designates the tree or even to a
park, two thousand אמות, amos, right?
And he puts the food under this tree, two thousand אמות, amos,
right? And if he wants to go see a next friend, to
sit down with somebody else, he wants to go away five hundred
feet?
Right, you can.
You can go two thousand אמות amos from wherever you put down
the food or from wherever you designate.
From where you put down the food you can go two
thousand אמות amos in a circle. Right, exactly. Now actually, the question
about the circle and how you measure it is exactly what the
גמרא Gemara is now going to turn to, because now that we've
gotten dealt with the issues about the tree, which was all of
the last two days, the end of the משנה Mishna discusses how
you measure the two thousand אמות. amos. In a circle, in a
square, or what? Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara actually gets to
the core of the issue of where we know this whole idea
of two thousand אמות amos to begin with and how you measure
it. So let's take a look. הני אלפים אמה, Hani alpaim amah,
if everybody sees again, it's like fifteen lines down, אם אינו מכירה
או שאינו בקי. Im eino makiro o she'eino baki. הני אלפים אמה,
Hani alpaim amah,
says the גמרא, Gemara, these
two thousand אמות, amos, היכן כתיבן? Heichan ksivan? Where are they written?
Again, assuming that it's based on a פסוק, pasuk, because this whole
idea of עירוב תחומין, eiruv techumim, you know, where do we get
it from anyway? And where do we get the particulars from, where
do we get the whole idea from? So the answer where we
get it from is where משה Moshe says by the מן, man,
שבו איש תחתיו, shvu ish tachtav, everybody sit in your place. אל
יצא איש ממקומו ביום השביעי. Al yetze ish mimkomo bayom hashvi'i. People
should not leave right where their place on the seventh day. As
people, I think, are aware, you know, the צדוקים, Tzadokim, whatever, didn't
leave at all, didn't go out at all. Or was it just
the צדוקים Tzadokim or was it the קראים? Karaites? It was the
קראים. Karaites. Okay, I don't remember, right. Anyway, so for חז״ל, Chazal,
they interpreted it in a more limited way. First of all, there's
a question if it's biblical or not; maybe it just means don't
go checking for the מן. man. Doesn't have to literally be meaning
you can't go out. And even if it is biblical, the רמב״ם
Rambam understands it's only biblical at twelve times the limit that חז״ל
Chazal put it to: at twenty-four thousand אמות, amos, at twelve מיל,
mil, not at one מיל. mil. But anyway, that's the פסוק, pasuk,
whether it's biblical or an אסמכתא asmachta that they're basing themselves on.
So it says, הני אלפים אמה היכן כתיבן, Hani alpaim amah heichan
ksivan, where do you get this from? דתניא, Detanya, שבו איש תחתיו,
shvu ish tachtav, every person sit in your place. אלו ארבע אמות.
Elu arba amos. These are the four אמות, amos, and we've learned
before, תחתיו, tachtav, your space is defined by four אמות. amos. So
when you're outside of the תחום, techum, you only have four אמות;
amos; you're extremely limited. אל יצא איש ממקומו, Al yetze ish mimkomo,
do not leave your מקום. makom. Not—תחתיו tachtav is about like directly
underneath you, sit where you are. מקום makom is bigger; מקום, makom,
your space, is bigger than like just where you're standing. So what's
your מקום? makom? אלו אלפים אמה, Elu alpaim amah, that's two
thousand אמות. amos. All right, very nice, but where do you get
two thousand אמות amos from that פסוק? pasuk? מנלן, Minalan, where does
that come from? אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, למדנו מקום ממקום
ומקום מניסה וניסה מניסה וניסה מגבול וגבול מגבול וגבול מחוץ וחוץ מחוץ.
Lamadnu makom mimakom umakom minisah unisah minisah unisah migvul ugvul migvul ugvul
michutz vechutz michutz. Okay,
so it's like a daisy chain of linked פסוקים, psukim, okay.
You link פסוק pasuk A to פסוק pasuk B, and B to
C, and C to D, and D to E, and E to
F, and in F it says two thousand אמות. amos. And in
A it said אל יצא איש ממקומו. al yetze ish mimkomo. So
through the daisy chain you're openly able to get to פסוק pasuk
F where it says two thousand אמות. amos. How does the daisy
chain work? In every link of that chain you have a linking
word. Okay, so the link between A and B—here it says אל
יצא איש
ממקומו—so al yetze ish mimkomo the link between A and B is
another place where it says מקום. makom. Okay, now in that place
B where it says מקום, makom, it also says ניסה, nisah, and
ניסה nisah links to C where it says ניסה, nisah, right? And
then ניסה nisah links to D where it says ניסה nisah and
גבול. gvul. And גבול gvul links to E where it says, thank
you, גבול gvul and חוץ. chutz. So you get the idea: every
one of those links of the chain has one word connecting it
to the prior and one word connecting it to the... to the
next. So what are those פסוקים psukim *pesukim*? So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* does not quote you what the פסוקים psukim. *pesukim* are, רש״י
Rashi, *Rashi* is. If you take a look at רש״י Rashi, *Rashi*,
here we'll look at רש״י *Rashi*, we have a little time, so
it says מקום ממקום ומקום מניסא *makom mi-makom u-makom mi-nisa* about I
don't know 20 lines down in the narrow lines of רש״י *Rashi*:
פסוק passuk שנאמר בו מקום ולא נאמר בו ניסא דנין אותו מפסוק
אחר שנאמר בו מקום וניסא כגון *pasuk shene'emar bo makom ve-lo ne'emar
bo nisa danin oto mi-pasuk acher shene'emar bo makom ve-nisa k'gon*. And
now here's where he shows you the פסוקים psukim. *pesukim*: אל יצא
איש ממקומו *al yeitzei ish mi-mekomo*. So that's the פסוק passuk *pasuk*,
don't leave your place. דנין *danin*, you connect that, you learn it
from ושמתי לך
מקום אשר ינוס שמה *ve-samti lecha makom asher yanus shamah*. That's the
ניסא *nisa*, running. Okay, so that's from the ערי מקלט *arei miklat*.
So and then he says, he skips a little, I'll skip a
little, then it says like four lines down, והדר דנין ניסא מניסא
וניסא מגבול כלומר דנין ניסא זו שלא נאמר בו גבול מניסא שנאמר
בו גבול דכתיב מגבול עיר מקלטו אשר ינוס *ve-hadar danin nisa mi-nisa
ve-nisa mi-gevul klomar danin nisa zo she-lo ne'emar bo gevul mi-nisa shene'emar
bo gevul d'chtiv mi-gevul ir miklato asher yanus*. Okay, so basically he
quotes all the פסוקים *pesukim*. Maybe a little complicated, it's a little
bit too much reading into רש״י *Rashi*, but just to go back,
right, our פסוק passuk *pasuk* says אל יצא איש ממקומו *al yeitzei
ish mi-mekomo*, that's מקום *makom*. The next פסוק passuk, *pasuk* it says
ושמתי לך מקום אשר ינוס שמה *ve-samti lecha makom asher yanus shamah*.
So you link מקום *makom* to מקום *makom* and now you get
the פסוק passuk *pasuk* לנוס *lanus*. And that לנוס *lanus* connects to
another פסוק *pasuk* that says מגבול עיר מקלטו אשר ינוס *mi-gevul ir
miklato asher yanus*. Okay,
so that לנוס *lanus* gives you another פסוק *pasuk* that says גבול
*gevul*, and that גבול *gevul* says is linked to a פסוק *pasuk*
that says חוץ *chutz*. What's the פסוק *pasuk* that says חוץ *chutz*?
ומצא אותו גואל הדם או ברש״י מחוץ michutz. לעיר מקלטו *u-matza oto
goel ha-dam o be-Rashi mi-chutz li-ir miklato*. And that חוץ *chutz* links
to a פסוק *pasuk* that says 2,000 אמה amah *amah*. What's the
final פסוק *pasuk* that says 2,000 אמה amah *amah*? דכתיב וחוץ מחוץ
דכתיב *d'chtiv ve-chutz mi-chutz d'chtiv* back to the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* ומדותם
מחוץ לעיר אל פאת קדמה אלפים באמה *u-madotem mi-chutz la-ir el pe'at
kedmah alpayim ba-amah*. So basically this is a long daisy chain to
get you to where the תורה Torah *Torah* speaks about the cities
of the לויים Levi'im *Levi'im*. It says outside of the cities of
the לויים Levi'im *Levi'im* you have a like a, you know, a
plot, you have like a it's a מגרש *migrash*, you know, a
field, a field that surrounds the city. And those fields, it first
says they're 2,000 אמה amah *amah* around the city and then it
says they're 1,000 אמה *amah* around the city. So basically the first
1,000 אמה *amah* is for more using it for like you know
planting and whatever, the next 1,000 אמה *amah* is just to let
them lay fallow and some space around the city. But there's this
surrounding area around the cities of the לויים Levi'im, *Levi'im* that are
2,000 אמה *amah*. And those and so basically through a daisy chain
where we link the פסוקים *pesukim* that says that you should be
in your place to פסוק *pasuk* B and B to C and
C to D and D to E and eventually we get to
a פסוק *pasuk* that speaks about the 2,000 אמה *amah* around the
cities of the לויים Levi'im, *Levi'im*. Okay? So that's how you know
2,000 אמה *amah*. דכתיב ומדותם מחוץ לעיר *d'chtiv u-madotem mi-chutz la-ir* you
shall measure outside the city פאת קדמה אלפים באמה *pe'at kedmah alpayim
ba-amah* 2,000 אמה *amah* outside the city.
So you see the area around your city is 2,000 אמה *amah*
so we will similarly say the area around where you start שבת
Shabbos *Shabbos*, if you start שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos* in a city then
it's 2,000 אמה *amah* around the city and if you start שבת
Shabbos *Shabbos* outside of a city it's 2,000 אמה *amah* from where
you begin and that's your תחום techum *tchum*. So now the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says ונילף מקיר העיר וחוצה אלף אמה *ve-neilef mi-kir ha-ir
ve-chutza elef amah*. There's another פסוק *pasuk* that says חוץ *chutz* and
doesn't say אלפים *alpayim* 2,000 but says 1,000 אמה *amah* because as
I mentioned to you the פסוקים *pesukim* that talk about the area
around the cities of לויים *Levi'im* some say 2,000 אמה *amah* and
some say 1,000 אמה *amah*. So why do you learn it from
the 2,000 אמה *amah* פסוק *pasuk*? Learn it from the 1,000 אמה
*amah* פסוק *pasuk*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says דנין חוץ מחוץ
ואין דנין חוץ מחוצה *danin chutz mi-chutz ve-ein danin chutz mi-chutza*. Because
to link the פסוקים *pesukim* like the end of the daisy chain
the word right before it said ומצא אותו גואל הדם מחוץ לגבול
עיר מקלטו *u-matza oto goel ha-dam mi-chutz li-gevul ir miklato*. So outside
מחוץ *mi-chutz* עיר מקלטו *ir miklato*. And the פסוק *pasuk* of 2,000
אמה *amah* said ומדותם מחוץ לעיר *u-madotem mi-chutz la-ir*.
So it's the exact same word מחוץ *mi-chutz* and מחוץ *mi-chutz*. So
that's why we link it to the פסוק *pasuk* of 2,000. The
פסוק *pasuk* of 1,000 says חוצה chutza *chutza*. So it's the same
idea of outside but it's not the exact same right grammatical form.
It's חוצה chutza *chutza* and not מחוץ *mi-chutz*. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says ומאי נפקא מינה *u-mai nafka mina* who cares? They're essentially
the same word and you're allowed to make a גזירה שוה gezeira
shava *gezeira shava* you're allowed to link פסוקים *pesukim* even if it's
not precise. התנא דבי רבי ישמעאל *Ha-tanna d'vei Rabbi Yishmael* we taught
in the house of רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* ושב הכהן ובא הכהן
*ve-shav ha-kohen u-va ha-kohen*. This is by very complicated פסוקים *pesukim* regarding
to צרעת *tzara'at* you know of the houses the like leprosy-type spots
that appears in houses where it says you know you tear out
the stones and you scrape it and then if it returns. And
anyway they learn certain הלכות halachos *halachos* from linking a פסוק *pasuk*
that talks about the כהן *kohen* returning. Now in one place where
it talks about the כהן *kohen* returning it says the כהן *kohen*
will return ושב הכהן *ve-shav ha-kohen*. In another place it talks about
the כהן *kohen* returning it says ובא הכהן *u-va ha-kohen* he'll come
he'll come to the house. But essentially they mean the same thing
the כהן *kohen* comes to the house. So because one פסוק *pasuk*
it says ושב *ve-shav* and one it says ובא *u-va* since essentially
they mean the same thing we're able to link those
פסוקים *pesukim* to.
So returning is the same as coming, just as long as you're
coming to that place. So therefore you see for גזירה שוה gezeira
shava the words don't have to be precise. So again, you got
from this פסוק of don't go out of your place, you made
a daisy chain of פסוקים that got you eventually to the idea
of 2,000 אמות, amot, why is it that you end with the
פסוק of 2,000, why not end with the פסוק of 1,000 that
also has the word חוצה in it? And חוצה is the pretty
much the same word as מחוץ. So the גמרא Gemara says no.
הני מילי היכא דליכא מידי דדמי ליה. hani mili heicha delika midi
dedami lei. That's when, when can you make a גזירה שוה gezeira
shava, in an imprecise map, when there's nothing that's more precise. אבל
היכא דאיכא מידי דדמי ליה, aval heicha de-ika midi dedami lei, if
there's something that's precisely like the other פסוק, מדדמי ליה ילפינן, midedami
lei yalfinan, you clearly will prefer making a גזירה שוה gezeira shava,
from a פסוק that is exactly alike. So here the גמרא Gemara
uses very
much
classic language of how it would treat a דאורייתא de-Oraita הלכה. halacha.
Where do you learn it out from?
גזירה שוה, gezeira shava and גזירה שוה, gezeira shava why do you
learn it this way, learn it that way, etc. etc. and makes
it sound like it's a דאורייתא. de-Oraita. Although as we know, the
dominant position is that this is all דרבנן, derabbanan, as I mentioned,
and even if it's דאורייתא de-Oraita רמב"ם Rambam says it's only 12
מיל mil not one מיל. mil. Now you do have similar things
elsewhere where the גמרא Gemara uses this language for something that's only
an אסמכתא. asmachta. Particularly what comes to mind because it's another one
of these daisy chain things is the גמרא Gemara in the beginning
of פסחים. Pesachim. The גמרא Gemara says how do you know that
you do בדיקת חמץ bedikat chametz with a candle, באור הנר? be-or
haneir? And makes a whole type of a list of a גזירה
שוה along this way. You'd link this to this and this to
this and this to this and this to this and you say
that the בדיקה bedika the best way to check is with candlelight.
Okay, now clearly the whole thing is דרבנן, derabbanan, the whole idea
of בדיקת חמץ bedikat chametz and using a candle and so on,
but still it uses this type of language even when it's doing
the אסמכתא. asmachta. Okay, so that's how we get to the 2,000
and the short version is that it learns it because when it
speaks about the area around the cities of לויים it's 2,000 אמות.
amot. So if we're going to speak about a space that you
have to
travel within these sort of environs of the city or your environs,
we'll learn it out from the cities of the לויים which is
2,000 אמות. amot. Okay, and now the גמרא Gomora turns to the
interesting question of do you measure them as a circle or as
a square? So the משנה Mishnah to remind you had the position
that you measure it as a circle, it's a 2,000 אמה radius
with you in the center. And then it said it was and
then that was one opinion. And the other opinion said here let's
just find it, where was this? This
was דף מ"ט עמוד ב'. daf mem tet amud bet. It says...
no not דף מ"ט עמוד ב', daf mem tet amud bet, one
minute. Yes, דף מ"ט עמוד ב'. daf mem tet amud bet. It
says שבת לו מקומו אלפיים אמה לכל רוח עגולות דברי רבי חנניה
בן אנטיגנוס.
shabbat lo mekomo alpayim amah lechol ruach agulot divrei rabbi
chananya ben antignos.
So רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina excuse me בן אנטיגנוס ben Antignos says
2,000 אמות amot in a circle. This is דף מ"ט עמוד ב'.
daf mem tet amud bet. וחכמים אומרים מרובעות כטבלא מרובעת, vachachamim omrim
meruba'ot ketavla meruba'at,
a square like a square טבלא, tavla, כדי שהן נשכר לזויות, kedei
she-hein nischar lazaviyot, you get the corners. Okay, so obviously if you
get a square where's my marker?
What is that טבלא, tavla, what does it mean by?
It just means like a tablet, just I don't know
what kind of tablet that they had in.
Well they had writing tablets. What kind of tablet did they have?
Well they had writing tablets like wax writing tablets that they would...
Parchment? No I thought they had wax no? I don't know, they
had writing tablets. Anyway, I don't have my pens, I think I
left them downstairs, you can see if they're in that. But anyway,
if you're here in the center and you make a 2,000 אמה
circle, I think you need a square to give you the more
exact idea. But anyway fine, you get the circle, but if you
make the 2,000 אמות amot gets you to a side,
and then you draw a square around that side, you're obviously going
to get the corners of that square that's going to be more
space if you walk at an angle. So that is the second
opinion. So let's take a look where you get this debate comes
from. So the גמרא Gomora says רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס מאי טעמא?
Rabbi Chanina ben Antignos mai ta'ama? So the גמרא Gomora says the
position that needs explaining is the one that says circle. Why? At
least circle makes sense, it's 2,000 אמות amot in every direction. But
no, here's why we don't understand it. אי אית ליה גזירה שוה,
ei it lei gezeira shava, if he has the גזירה שוה the
linking that we mentioned above that you learn it out from the
cities of the לויים, then פאה כתיבן. pe'ah ketivan. There it says
פאה, pe'ah, it says the פאה pe'ah the corner of the east
and the פאה, pe'ah, the פאה pe'ah the side of the west
and so on. That the use of the word
פאה pe'ah indicates the idea that there are corners. Means, so it
understands that when the תורה draws the area around the cities of
לויים, it is drawing a square around the area cities. Not a
circle. So if your basis is the city of לויים *Levi'im*, you
should have corners. אי לית ליה גזירה שוה *i leis lei gezeirah
shavah*, and if you don't learn it out from the לויים *Levi'im*,
you don't make that link, אלפי אמה מנלן *alfei ammah minnalan*? Where
do you get the whole idea of 2,000 אמות amos, *ammot*, right?
So where do you get the idea of 2,000 but that it's
a circle, not a square? Says the גמרא Gomora *Gemara*, לעולם אית
ליה גזירה שוה *le'olam is lei gezeirah shavah*. He holds of the
גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah*. So why does he go only give why
does he give it a circle and not a square? ושאני הכא
דאמר קרא *v'shani hacha d'amar kra* because the פסוק *passuk* by the
לויים *Levi'im* ends זה יהיה לכם מגרשי הערים *zeh yihyeh lahem migrashiei
he'arim*. This should be for them, their sort of, you know, the
fields around their cities. לזה אתה נותן פאה *l'zeh attah noten pe'ah*.
For them, for the לויים *Levi'im*, the לויים *Levi'im* get their corners.
Meaning yes, you learn it from the לויים *Levi'im* but there's something
that is only זה *zeh*, that's only for them that is doesn't
apply elsewhere. What is this? The idea of including the corners. לזה
אתה נותן פאה ואי אתה נותן פאה לשובתי שבת Shabbos, *l'zeh attah
noten pe'ah v'ee attah noten pe'ah l'shovsei Shabbos*. But you don't give
the corners to people that for for שבת Shabbat *Shabbos* purposes. There
you go circles, not squares. Okay, so he learns לזה *l'zeh* is
a limiting word. ורבנן *v'rabbanan*,
so what would the רבנן *rabbanan* say back? So תני רבי חנניה
Rabbi Chananya, *tani Rabi Chananiah*, standard רבי חנניה Rabbi Chananya. *Rabi Chananiah*
not to be confused with רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina *Rabi Chanina*, but
רבי חנניה *Rabi Chananiah* had a ברייתא beraisa *braisa* that has that
explains how the רבנן *rabbanan* would respond to the פסוק *passuk*. ורבנן
*v'rabbanan*, תני ברייתא braita רבי חנניה אומר *tani braisa Rabi Chananiah omer*,
רבי חנניה *Rabi Chananiah* says, כזה יהיו כל שובתי שבת Shabbat *kezeh
yihyu kol shovsei Shabbos*. Not לזה *l'zeh*, not this in exclusion of
שובתי שבת Shabbat *shovsei Shabbos*, of שבת Shabbat *Shabbos*, but it says
זה יהיה לכם *zeh yihyeh lahem*, this, just like this should be
everything else. So, there's a question about what do you do with
the פסוק *passuk*. Again, quite fascinating that we're learning it from a
פסוק *passuk* and it seems to treat it as it treats normal,
you know, דאורייתא de'oraisa *d'Oraisa* about how do you learn it this
way, learn it that way. But again, understanding that probably this is
all an אסמכתא asmachta *asmachta*, but anyway, we learn from the לויים
*Levi'im* 2,000 אמות amos *ammot*, but it says זה *zeh*, this. So
רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina, *Rabi Chanina* says זה *zeh* means only this
is treated as a square, other things as a circle. And the
רבנן *rabbanan* say everything you treat as a square of 2,000 אמות
amos. *ammot* just like the לויים *Levi'im* even by שבת Shabbat *Shabbos*.
Now this is fine. That's one question about תחומין techumin *techumin*. But
now we're going to turn to something that is a real דאורייתא
*d'Oraisa*. Before we get to that I should just though make a
point, which is what do we think that means that you do
a square? How do you draw the square? I really need my
this is where I need my my marker. But anyway, here, what?
All right, I'll just use this.
This is your square, right? So if your city is a circle
like this, or whatever your city is, let's say you're an individual
and you're starting here. Do you draw the square like this? And
then you can go, you know, this way, you know, you get
these angles that are longer? Or do you just draw the square
like this and you can get this way that's longer? Right? Which
direction do you draw the square in? So, we're going to see
later that when it comes and this becomes even more important when
it comes to demarcating the the boundaries of a city. Like and
really important if you're like in Manhattan, right? Because let's say here,
let's say you're like this is like Manhattan, right? This sort of
is like Manhattan looks like, like this, right? Now you have to
square off the city. So if you square it off, meaning if
you just sort of do like this, let's say, make a square
sort of like this, that's one thing. But what we're going to
find out is that when you square off the city, you square
it off based on the corners of the points of the compass.
So you take the northernmost point, right, the like, you know, easternmost,
the southernmost, the westernmost and you go to draw a square like
this. See what I mean? You draw a square like that. Not
just you make a simple smooth out the edges. You actually draw
a square so the sides are to the compass sides. So if
you're doing a city like Manhattan, you're going to get a whole
huge corner here, right, almost double the size of it because of
the way you're drawing the square. So the assumption here is the
same. That wherever you start שבת Shabbat *Shabbos*, you draw the square
to the corners of the to the points of the compass. And
therefore if you go due north or due south, you only have
2,000 אמות amos. *ammot* or east or west. If you go to
45 angle northeast or you know or southeast, then you have 2,000
times the square root of 2, which is 2,800 or so. Okay,
so that is no, is that right? Yes. Okay. So that is
that you draw a square and the assumption here being, although I'll
discuss alternatives in a minute, that you draw the square according to
the points of the compass and as I said, we'll see the
same about when you square off a city.
So this applies to your going to the tree because it seems
to me like if your house is more than 2,000 אמות amos,
*ammot* away from where you are and you pick a tree, depending
on how the compass orientates it, you should be able to go
like 2,200.
Exactly. So all the cases before then about saying that you can
get to the tree if it's 2,000 אמות amot *ammot* assumes that
the tree is like due east or due north. But if this
tree is at an angle, then you know you get more. Exactly.
At least according to the רבנן *rabbanan* that say you draw a
square. So it says, okay. So now that's just about this thing
which is rabbinic, most probably. But now we're going to get a
shocking statement. אמר Amar, רבי אחא בר יעקב *Amar Rabi Acha bar
Yaakov*, המעביר ארבע אמות ברשות הרבים arba amos birshus harabbim, *hameavir arba
ammos b'reshus harabbim*. If somebody carries four אמות amot in רשות הרבים,
reshus harabbim, אינו חייב עד שמעביר הן ואלכסונן. eino chayav ad shemavir
hen v'alachsonan. You're not חייב chayav until you do not only four
אמות, amot, but you do four אמות amot. and the hypotenuse of
a four by four square until you do 5.6 אמות. amot So
we've been learning since מסכת שבת, Masechet Shabbos, we've now learned about
200 דפים dapim of גמרא Gemara. where it's always been ארבע אמות
arba amos, ברשות הרבים, and we get to the point that says
you know what, it's not ארבע אמות, arba amos, it's the like
it's the hypotenuse, it's 5.6, it's four times the square root of
two.
So now where do we get this from? אמר רב פפא בדיק
לן רבא, Amar Rav Pappa badik lanu Rava, so רבא Rava asked
us. So that was one issue about carrying. Now we're going to
another issue. עמוד ברשות הרבים גבוה י' ורחב ד'. Amud birshus harabbim
gavoh yud v'rachav arba. When you have a pole in רשות הרבים
reshus harabbim that is ten tall and four wide, ten טפחים tefachim
tall and four by four wide. So when we say that that's
a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid,
צריך הן ואלכסונן או לא? tzarich hen v'alachsonan o lo? Do you
need for the four, do you need it to be the angle
or do you just need it to be a straight four? Do
you need it to be four times the square root of two?
Good
question. What? Well let's take a look what his answer is. Okay
he said ואמינא ליה v'aminan lei and we said לאו היינו דרבי
חנינא? lav haynu d'Rabbi Chanina? Isn't this what רבי חנינא said? דתניא
d'tanya we learned in a ברייתא Braisah רבי חנניה, I mean not
רבי חנינא, רבי חנניה. רבי חנניה אומר כזה הוא כל שבשבת. Rabbi
Chananya omer kazehu kol sheb'Shabbos. We learn from the idea of the
square of the city of the לוויים Levi'im that it applies by
שבת Shabbos. as well. So now what does that mean? So now
that means that what? That a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid by שבת,
Shabbos which we always said was ארבע, arba, is also not ארבע,
arba, it's 5.6. Like this is upturning our world. We always said
carrying for שבת Shabbos is ארבע אמות, arba amos. now he's saying
it's 5.6.
He said a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid is what is ארבע, arba,
now he's saying it's 5.6. So what does it mean? Why doesn't
it make sense? Also by the way it shows, I should just
say before we get to explaining the different ways in what this
might mean, it shows that the גמרא Gemara is treating seriously the
idea that we really learned this from the פסוקים. Whatever you say
about תחומין tchumin, being דרבנן, derabbanan, here we're really learning real דאורייתא
הלכות from the פסוקים. So I'm going to give you a couple
of variations, but first I want to hear from Dov why it
doesn't make sense.
The only way this question could make sense is if you're talking
about this kind of thing where this is four and four and
he's asking do the corners have to be filled in? Aha. But
if you're asking does four by four really mean 5.6 by 5.6,
that doesn't make sense because if you have four by four, you
have four by four.
Okay so I will tell you the different variations of what this
might mean. First I'll tell you in terms of the carrying and
maybe I'll just use this as a visual aid. First I'll tell
you in terms of the carrying and then I'll tell you in
terms of the רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. So in terms of the
carrying,
there's two positions about what this means. רש"י Rashi says, or whatever,
the second position in תוספות, Tosfos, רש"י Rashi is a little vague,
anyway רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam says to at least tame this idea
a little bit, that no, it depends again which direction you're carrying
in. If you carry an object, it's still a little wild, but
if you carry an object due east or due north or due
south, it's ארבע אמות. arba amos But if you carry an object
northeast at a 45-degree angle, you have to carry it 5.6 אמות.
amot. Which that at least to some degree makes sense. If what
we're saying is the way we conceptualize the space of something, whether
it's your space and the space is 2000 אמות, amos whether it's
the object's zone, the object's space, and that's ארבע אמות arba amos
in each direction, or if you're caught outside of the תחום tchum,
and you have ארבע אמות arba amos. in each direction, the way
we conceptualize it is you're in a square defined by the compass
points. And if you think that carrying is not just the act
of moving it a particular distance, but the idea of carrying is
taking it out of its location. So you had an object that
was here, and you're carrying in רשות הרבים reshus harabbim if you
move it from its original location. So if you go this way,
you've removed it from its original location. If you go this way,
you haven't yet, if you conceptualize that the space of something is
defined by a square by the compass points. Also if you're going
at an angle, you have to take it out 5.6. That's the
way רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam says. The other opinion in תוספות Tosfos
says that any direction you carry it in is 5.6, which is
crazy. So we've always been talking about ארבע arba and it's really
a shorthand of saying 5.6. I mean so at least the second
opinion is a little more reasonable, okay ארבע arba when you're going
in certain directions, different when you're going in other directions. So that's
number one that just changes. I mean again it's amazing. We've learned
a מסכת masechet and a half about carrying and now we first
find out it's not always ארבע אמות. arba amos, Now how about
the idea of רשות היחיד? reshus hayachid? So here what רש"י Rashi
sounds like is רש"י Rashi sounds like the question is about
whether a much simpler question. When I say ten טפחים tefachim and
four by four, does it have to be a circle four by
four? Does it have to be a square four by four? And
the whole answer of הן ואלכסונן hen v'alachsonan at the end by
רשות היחיד... reshus hayachid... means, it’s not enough to have a circle
that has
a—that’s—that’s has a radius of—actually, it would be a radius of two—so
it’s like a total of four, at the diameter would be four,
but it actually needs to be a square עמוד amud or an
עמוד amud that you could square
off, four by four. Which, according to that, that’s fine, that’s what
we’ve always assumed. Whenever you say something is a certain dimension in
הלכה, Halacha, you almost always mean a square. Like if a טפח
tefach by a טפח tefach carries טומאה tumah or is a window
between two spaces for the transfer of טומאה, tumah, right, we mean
that it’s not a טפח tefach circle, but we mean it’s a
טפח tefach square. Like if the size of a סוכה sukkah has
to be four אמות amot by four אמות amot or seven טפחים
tefachim by seven טפחים, tefachim, we mean a square that size, not
a circle that size, which is in addition to the corners. So
according to רש״י, the end of the גמרא Gemara is just saying
that it just need when we measure, four by four by
רשות היחיד, Reshus Hayachid, we’re measuring the square, not a circle. תוספות
Tosfos has two other explanations. The explanation that he said, the more
radical one, that says every number we’ve ever seen really means times
the square root of two, so that therefore a רשות היחיד Reshus
Hayachid is not four by four, it’s 5.6 by 5.6. Again, that’s
pretty radical. And the other explanation of רבנו תם, Rabbeinu Tam, which
is consistent, which says it depends how your רשות היחיד Reshus Hayachid
is situated. If your רשות היחיד Reshus Hayachid is situated based on
the compass points, then it’s four by four. If your רשות היחיד
Reshus Hayachid were situated like this, right, even if it was four
by four, you would not be חייב chayav because it needs to
be—right, because it needs to be—I’ll explain exactly what that means. Right,
if this is your רשות היחיד, Reshus Hayachid, if it’s situated like
this, it’s four by four, you measure it by the compass points.
But if it’s situated like this, even if it’s the same four-by-four
square, you would not be חייב chayav because you need—I guess what
it’s saying is—that you need the northeast angle to be four times
the square root of two. Basically, you need it to be a
four by four that fits to the compass points. Okay, so that’s
the way רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam reads it. So it is actually
quite fascinating, this little גמרא Gemara that seemed to just be an
אסמכתא about תחומין, t-chumin comes to radically potentially change our idea of
how much do you have to carry and what defines a רשות
היחיד. Reshus Hayachid. So just to review the opinions. When it comes
to carrying,
one opinion is you always need to carry 5.6. The other opinion,
which is רבנו תם, Rabbeinu Tam’s, which makes a lot more sense,
is that you have to
carry—you have to carry it out of its space, and its space
is defined as a four by four אמה square based on the
compass points. So based on which direction you carry it, we would
determine if you carried it out of its space. In some directions,
only four אמות, amot in other directions you have to carry it
longer. And in terms of what makes a רשות היחיד, Reshus Hayachid,
so according to רש״י, the גמרא Gemara really didn’t say anything new.
The גמרא Gemara just said that it has to be a square
four by four, not a circular. According to one opinion, even a
רשות היחיד Reshus Hayachid needs 5.6, and according to רבנו תם, Rabbeinu
Tam, it has to be four by four along the compass points.
So based on how it’s situated, you would have to be able
to square off four by four by the compass points even if
you had a four-by-four square.
Yes. This four by four is with you in the middle of
the square, with two in each direction or it’s four in each
direction?
So by the cases of
רשות היחיד, Reshus Hayachid, it’s four in each direction, not with you
in the middle. By the cases of carrying,
it’s four in each direction, because if you carry it in one
direction four אמות. amot By the case of the תחום, tchum, it’s
well, 2000 in each direction, but if you’re outside the תחום, techum
we saw that that was debated before. Some say two in each
direction and some say four. But in terms of the carrying issues,
carrying is four in any particular direction, or here we see four
in the compass points, more in other points. But the רשות reshus
is four on each side.
Okay, so if you carry something three and a half אמות amos.
in this direction, come back to your starting point, and go three
and a half אמות.
Yeah, that we always knew. But the חידוש chidush is you can
carry something 5.5 at an angle, and you haven’t transgressed שבת, Shabbos
but if you carried it due north, it would only be able
to—once you did four, you would have transgressed. Right, so it’s quite
shocking. Yes.
That also calls another opinion, which is more appealing because
it doesn’t fix you into the north-south thing. What he says is,
if you have—you could be like this, you could be like this,
he defines a circle based on all the possible endpoints of the
square.
Right, so you square it off wherever it is.
Yeah, but no, you circle around all the possible squares, so you
have a circle whose diameter
is 5.6.
Right, that’s the position I was saying, you always need 5.6.
Yeah, yeah, but he’s saying it’s not—you also have—you can also go
in whichever direction.
You can go 5.6. Yeah, not
just... Quite a
shocking גמרא Gemara *Gemara* for that. And as I said by the
way, I know most of us aren't planning on carrying on שבת
Shabbos, *Shabbos* in a רשות הרבים *reshus harabim*, so four versus five
point six doesn't make such a difference, but this will make a
huge difference when it comes to figuring out the תחום techum *t'chum*
of a city. Because you want to figure out the תחום techum
*t'chum* of New York, right, you actually get a much larger space
than you would have imagined. It actually overlaps with New Jersey. Because
if you looked at a map and drew a square around New
York based on the compass points, you would get a good section
of New Jersey. Okay, so so it really does matter this idea
of drawing a square and drawing it by the compass points. Alright,
so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. וזו היא שאמרו V'zu hi
she'amru, העני מערב ברגליו *ve-zo-hi she-amru ha-ani me'arev beraglav*. So the משנה
Mishnah, *Mishnah* says, so this idea you're caught outside the city or
whatever or you say I'll start שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* here, this is
where they said an עני ani. *ani* can make an עירוב eruv
*eruv* with his own feet. You don't have to use a loaf
of bread. אמר רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. *Amar Rabbi Meir*, רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* said, אנו אין לנו אלא עני ani. *anu
ein lanu ela ani*. It only applies to an עני ani *ani*
and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. *Rabbi Yehuda* says it applies to an
עני ani *ani* or an עשיר ashir. *ashir*. The loaf of bread
was just to be easy on you. So
so here רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* limits the idea of
doing it in person with the עני ani. *ani*. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says like this.
אמר רב נחמן Rav Nachman
*Amar
Rav Nachman*, said רב נחמן Rav Nachman *Rav Nachman*, מחלוקת במקומי *machlokes
bimkomi*. The debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, *Rabbi Meir* and רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* whether it applies to an עשיר ashir,
*ashir*, somebody who has bread, or just an עני ani, *ani*, is
the last case in the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* where you say I
want my עירוב eruv? *eruv* to start where I'm standing. That even
in that case, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. *Rabbi Meir* limits it to
an עני ani *ani*. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. סבר עיקר עירוב eruv
בפת *Rabbi Meir savar ikar eruv be-pas*. Fundamentally the עירוב eruv *eruv*,
even עירוב תחומין eruv techumin? *eruv techumim*, we know it's true about
עירוב eruv, חצירות *eruv chatzeiros*, but even עירוב eruv, תחומין techumin, *eruv
techumim* was fundamentally about an idea of placing bread. And therefore, עני
ani הוא דהקילו רבנן עליה *ani hu de-hakilu Rabbanan ilei*. For an
עני ani *ani*, the Rabbis went lenient and said you don't have
bread, so we'll let you do it in person. אבל עשיר ashir
*Aval ashir*, if you had bread available to you, עשיר ashir? *ashir*
does not mean, you know, we look at your net income. עשיר
ashir *ashir* just means you had bread available. Everybody who's stuck on
the way has nothing on them is considered an עני ani *ani*.
Okay for this purposes. But an עשיר ashir לא *ashir lo*, they
wouldn't allow him even if you wanted to go there personally. ורבי
יהודה סבר עיקר עירוב eruv, ברגל *Verabbi Yehuda savar ikar eruv baregel*.
No, fundamentally עירוב eruv. *eruv* is where your feet are, where you
start שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos* physically. אחד עני ואחד עשיר echad ani v'echad
ashir. *Echad ani ve-echad ashir*, and whether an עני ani. *ani* or
an עשיר ashir *ashir*, anybody can say they start שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos*
where they're standing. אבל *Aval*, so that's what they debate, if you
want to start שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* where you're standing. אבל במקום פלוני
*Aval bimkom ploni*, how about the first case of the משנה Mishnah,
*Mishnah*? The first case of the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* you remember was
a חידוש chiddush. *chiddush*. Was like you were saying my שבת Shabbat
*Shabbos* is going to start two thousand אמות *amos* away from where
I'm standing at that tree over there. So you didn't put bread
by the tree, you weren't standing by the tree, you just designated
the tree. Okay, that's a big חידוש *chiddush*. We always said you
had to be there or you had to put bread there. So
that idea where you can say that it's a distant spot that
you're designating, that is only by the case of the guy stuck
on the way. אבל במקום פלוני *Aval bimkom ploni*, when you want
to say in such and such a place, דברי הכל divrei hakol,
*divrei hakol*, everybody would agree, even רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. *Rabbi Yehuda*,
עני ani, אין עשיר ashir לא *ani in ashir lo*. That it
only could be a poor person and here poor meaning the guy
stuck out in the middle of the road and has nothing, is
no other possibility. Can't put bread there, can't be there physically. Right,
that was the big חידוש *chiddush*. We said yesterday, by the way,
that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* curtailed this חידוש *chiddush* a little bit,
said you had to be able to run to that place and
get there before it got dark. That you can't say I start
שבת Shabbat? *Shabbos* there, I start שבת Shabbat *Shabbos* there if it
wasn't physically able for you to be there before it got dark.
So this is a special leniency they allowed the guy stuck on
the road, and everybody would agree it's only in that special case.
Okay, and then the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* goes on and says וזו
היא שאמרו *ve-zo-hi she-amru*. So the משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah* is, so if
you take a look, I mean you have to look, turn back
and look at the text of the משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah* because it's
important. On מ"ט עמוד א *mem-tes amud aleph*, okay, we'll see what
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is trying to parse the text of the
משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*.
So it says like this,
so it says,
so it says like this, וזו היא שאמרו *ve-zo-hi she-amru*, if you
see it, it's like this by an asterisk, it's מ"ט עמוד ב
*mem-tes amud beis*, it's like five lines before the word גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* appears underneath it. Okay, so after it deals with the case
about the guy saying I'll start שבת Shabbat *Shabbos* where I am,
וזו היא שאמרו העני מערב ברגליו *ve-zo-hi she-amru ha-ani me'arev beraglav*. So
that's where they say an עני ani *ani* can do it with
his feet. אמר רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir אין לנו אלא עני ani
*Amar Rabbi Meir ein lanu ela ani*, רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda
omer, אחד עני ואחד עשיר echad ani ve-echad ashir. *Rabbi Yehuda omer
echad ani ve-echad ashir*. So there's a debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir *Rabbi Meir* and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, *Rabbi Yehuda*, does it
apply to a rich person? And then it says, לא אמרו מערבין
בפת אלא להקל על העשיר *lo amru me'arvim be-pas ela lehakeil al
ha-ashir*. Do you use bread is only to be easy on the
עשיר ashir *ashir* but really you can actually do it with your
feet. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* wants to understand the two סתם
stam *stam* statements in this משנה Mishna *Mishnah*. זו היא שאמרו Zu
hi she'amru *zo-hi she-amru* which comes before רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. *Rabbi
Meir* and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. *Rabbi Yehuda*, that the עני ani
*ani* can do it with his feet and the statement after. the
reason they said bread was to go easy on the guy, who
are they being said according to? Now the simple read of the
משנה Mishna is that זו היא שאמרו עני מערב ברגליו Zu hi
she'amru ani me'arav b'raglav is רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir is emphasizing it's the עני. ani So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir,
says only an עני. ani, And then the last statement is רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says no, no, no, the,
they said bread to go easy on you, but anybody can do
it with their feet. So that's obviously the simple stance that the
first line is רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir the last line is רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda Let's look back at the גמרא. Gemara, So turning
back to נ' עמוד ב', nun amud bet, we have like this.
Okay, זו היא שאמרו quote unquote, מן תני לה? man tani lah?
So the first סתם line in the משנה, Mishna this is where
they said that it could be that it's an עני ani can
do it, that's רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir That's in the case of
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir והאי קאי, V'hai kai, which is it going
like? Which case is it referring to? אינו מכיר, eino makir, the
guy if you don't know a tree to designate, או שאינו בקי
בהלכה, o she'eino baki b'halakha, or you didn't know again that second
case in the משנה Mishna, where you didn't know that you could
designate a tree. So in that case you're trying to start שבת
Shabbat where you're standing and it says, ah, you want to start
שבת Shabbat where you're standing? That an עני ani is able to
do it. And רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says only an עני. ani
Okay. ולא אמרו Ve'lo amru now the last line of the משנה,
Mishna ולא אמרו מערבין בפת אלא להקל, Ve'lo amru me'arvin b'pat ela
l'hakel, when it says, oh, so no, no, no, no, actually bread
is to go lenient on you, anybody can do it where they're
standing, מן תני לה, man tani lah, who's telling that? רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda that's רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda So a lot of that
was pretty obvious. Okay, but the reason it's saying it is because
it's going to contrast it to the next statement. So the upshot
of all of this is the debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, about whether it has to be a
poor person or even a rich, is somebody who wants to start
שבת Shabbat, where they're standing. Okay, and then it makes sense that
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says anybody can do that. You want to
start where you're standing, doesn't say hey, anybody can do that. But
the, the case of the early case of the משנה Mishna, where
you can designate a place far away, everybody agrees that that is
only a very special case that you're stuck outside the city and
you have no and you're not able to put bread there and
you're not able to be there. That's the first approach. רב
חסדא אמר, Rav Hisda amar, now רב חסדא Rav Hisda says no.
מחלוקת במקום פלוני. machloket b'makom ploni. The debate is if you say
is, is when you're trying to designate a place, such and such
a place. That's where even in that case רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
lets anybody do that, which is wild. רבי מאיר סבר עני אין
עשיר לא. Rabbi Meir savar ani in ashir lo. That idea that
you can designate a place is only about an עני, ani does
not apply to an עשיר. ashir Makes sense, it's crazy to allow
you to designate a place. רבי יהודה סבר Rabbi Yehuda savar and
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda hold and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda holds אחד
עני ani ואחד עשיר. ashir That whether an עני ani? or an
עשיר, ashir which is crazy according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda why
would you ever bother going out to place? You could always stay
at home and just designate a place. Maybe it's saying אי נמי?
ei nami? Okay, so that's a pretty wild position of רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda that you can anybody can designate a place. אבל במקומי,
aval bimkomi, if you want to start שבת Shabbat where you physically
are, not to designate a distant place, דברי הכל אחד עני ואחד
עשיר, divrei hakol echad ani v'echad ashir, everybody would say that even
an עשיר ashir could do it. דעיקר עירוב ברגל, d'ikar eruv b'regel,
everybody would agree that of course you can start שבת Shabbat without
bread where you're standing. So the only debate was the special case
of designating it far away. וזו היא שאמרו, and when the משנה
Mishnah says this is the case that an עני ani, can do
it, so מן תני לה man tani lah again, since it emphasizes
an עני ani can do it, who is it saying it? It's
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir But which case is it that they're debating
whether it's an עני ani, or an עשיר? ashir The only case
they're debating is not when you're saying where you're standing, but the
case they're debating is when you're designating a faraway space. והאי קאי,
V'hai kai, which case are we referring to? אהא, Aha, on the
early case of the משנה. Mishnah, מי שבא בדרך וחשכה, Mi sheba
baderekh v'chashkha,
okay that it's dark and you're designating a faraway space. ולא אמרו
מערבין בפת אלא להקל, Ve'lo amru me'arvin b'pat ela l'hakel, and when
the end line says oh, really anybody can use their legs, the
idea of using bread is to go easy on you, מן תני
לה man tani lah who's teaching it? דברי הכל, everybody would agree
that if it's not about a faraway space you can use the
space that you're standing on. So basically just to step back because
that was a little you know whatever figuring out all the lines
of the משנה, Mishnah but it's very simple in the following way.
The first approach which is the approach of רב נחמן Rav Nachman.
is the one we would have assumed. That the idea of designating
a faraway space is a very special case, guy stuck outside of
the city, everybody agrees that's only in the special case. The debate
of רבי מאיר and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is you just, you,
you know you just want to make שבת Shabbat start where you're
standing. So רבי מאיר says no, even that will only allow for
an עני. ani If you have bread you should always use bread.
And רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says what are you talking about? As
long as you want to do it where you're standing you should
be allowed to do it where you're standing. That's the approach רב
נחמן Rav Nachman. makes a lot of sense. The approach of רב
חסדא Rav Hisda is quite shocking. It's that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
would go so their only debate is the case of designating a
faraway space, that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would even allow even an
עשיר ashir, to sit at home and designate a faraway space. Okay
and the end of the משנה Mishnah. that says that you can,
you don't need bread if you don't want to use bread, everybody
would agree to that if you want to designate the space you're
standing on. Okay and the whole debate is when you're designating a
faraway space.
Yes, how does this tie into or or not with that little
part we
That idea that you can designate a distant spot is a huge
חידוש. And why do you even need to do anything for עירוב
תחומין? Just designate a spot. So the first thing the גמרא Gemara
said yesterday was that that only works if in theory you can
get to it, if you can run and get there before it
gets dark. Here what the גמרא Gemara is saying is that it
only works in that special case that you're stuck outside the city.
If you have the ability to put bread there or you were
able to have planned it so you could actually have been there
yourself or whatever, we wouldn't allow it. We only allow it in
a case where you're stuck. Right, now that makes sense. That's what
the גמרא Gemara means when it says that's only an עני, ani,
and עני ani means in this particular case that like you have
no no no other options. But the shocker is that according to
רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would allow it in
every case, which is like wild. Okay, don't worry, the גמרא's going
to side with רב נחמן. Rav Nachman Okay, so תניא כוותיה דרב
נחמן, Tanya kavatei d'Rav Nachman, we taught like רב נחמן. Rav Nachman
אחד עני ואחד עשיר מערבין בפת, echad ani ve'echad ashir me'arvin bepas,
whether an עני or an עשיר ashir. you can use bread. ולא
יצא עשיר חוץ לתחום ויאמר שביתתי במקומי, velo yetze ashir chutz latchum
veyomar shevisisi bimkomi, and an עשיר ashir should not go out of
his house and go you know and and you know sit wherever
he wants outside the תחום t-chum or at the edge of the
תחום and say here's where I'm starting my שבת. Shabbat לפי שאמרו
מערבין ברגל אלא למי שבא בדרך וחשכה, lefi she'amru me'arvin beragel ela
lemi sheba baderech vechashcha, דברי רבי מאיר, divrei Rabbi Meir, because you're
not allowed to do this because they only said that you can
do it with your feet if you're going on the way and
it's getting dark, דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. But here where
you left your home and you know well before it was dark
and you were planning on starting your שבת Shabbat at this new
space, in that type of a case you could have taken bread
from the house. Now by the way רש"י Rashi says that here
what it becomes clear is עני versus עשיר ashir. doesn't you know
again just really mean are you starting from your house or are
you starting from outside your house. If you're starting in your house
we assume that even if you're very poor you have some food
around. Okay, so everybody is effectively an עשיר ashir. if you start
at home and were planning how am I going to set my
עירוב out there. So according to רבי מאיר, any case like that
where you start at home you have to use bread. The only
case they allow you to use your feet is you were stuck
outside of your home. Okay, but notice by the way what you're
trying to do is start שבת Shabbos where you physically are, not
at some distant place. You're actually going to the place and trying
to start שבת Shabbos where you are. And even in that case
where you're trying to start where you are, רבי מאיר said if
you started from your house you need to bring some food with
you and you can only start where you are when you actually
are outside of your home and are stuck. Okay, so that clearly
is like רב נחמן Rav Nachman said that the whole debate is
when you're trying to do it where you physically are, not when
you're designating a different space.
What if you're you're not in your home but you're within 2000
אמות of your home?
And you want to still start שבת, Shabbos do you
have to have like a loaf of bread in your home and
make an עירוב?
No, if you were coming from away from your home.
No, your home, your home, and you go out to מנחה. Mincha.
Right, so that's an interesting question. Right, let's say you're coming from
you stopped off there after having made a trip to the store,
right, you were doing some shopping before שבת Shabbos, and then you
went, right, what is defined as sort of being בדרך? baderech? So
we'll see a little bit about that in a minute. It's not
so clear but we'll see a little bit about that in a
minute. Okay, so that's what רבי מאיר says. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
אומר, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says, אחד עני ואחד עשיר מערבין ברגל,
echad ani ve'echad ashir me'arvin beragel, no, either an עני or an
עשיר ashir can do it where you're standing. ויצא עשיר חוץ לתחום
ויאמר שביתתי במקומי, veyetze ashir chutz latchum veyomar shevisisi bimkomi, and an
עשיר ashir. can go you know anybody can leave their house and
go to it's funny he says חוץ לתחום chutz latchum but it
means right to to say the edge of the
תחום and say שביתתי במקומי, shevisisi bimkomi, this is where I want
to start שבת. וזו היא עיקרו של עירוב, vezu hi ikaro shel
eruv, and that's the fundamental עירוב is without the bread is where
you actually physically
are. והתירו חכמים לבעל הבית לשלח עירובו ביד עבדו ביד בנו ביד
שלוחו, vehitiru chachamim leba'al habayit leshalach eruvo beyad avdo beyad beno beyad
shlucho, and the חכמים chachamim were lenient
and they allowed you to send your servant, your son, your messenger
בשביל להקל עליו bishvil lehakeil alav to make it easy to you.
So anyway before we go any further, again the key here is
you're debating the case about a place you are physically present. That
רבי מאיר says even if you're physically there we will not let
you make that עירוב without bread. The only time we'll let you
do that is if you were stuck outside of the house. But
if you were started from the house we will not allow it.
And רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says what are you talking about? Where
you physically are is the basic idea of where you start שבת.
Using bread is just a leniency. So this proves like רב נחמן
Rav Nachman that the debate is the case of starting שבת where
you're physically present. If you want to designate a faraway space that
everybody would agree is a spec is only in the special case
of being caught outside the house. Now the
ברייתא continues. אמר רבי יהודה, amar Rabbi Yehuda, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
said, מעשה באנשי בית ממל ובאנשי בית גוריון בארומה, ma'aseh be'anshei beis
mamal uve'anshei beis guryon be'aroma, there was a case with the people
of ממל Mamal and the people of and the people of גוריון
Guryon in ארומה, Aroma, this village, שהיו מחלקים גרוגרות וצימוקים לעניים בשני.
shehayu mechalkim gerogerot vetzimukim le'aniyim beshani.
They would hand out dried figs and raisins because I guess this
is stuff that you could store for a long period of time,
and they would hand it out to the poor during the period
of famine. So they were very wealthy, their houses were open to
the poor. ובאו עניי כפר שיחין ועניי כפר חנניה u'vau aniyei Kfar
Shichin v'aniyei Kfar Chananya
and the people of these two villages would come, and they would
want to come on שבת to get the you know to get
this food. So how would they come? They were presumably 4,000 אמות
away according to the story. So how would they come to this
city on שבת? So they would come ומחשכין על התחום, u'mechashchin al
hat-chum, they would wait by the edge of the תחום until it
got dark, and then their שבת would be 2,000 אמות out of
their village. And then ולמחרת, u'l'machrat, שבת morning, משכימים ובאים mashkimim u'vaim
they would come. So basically if they were 4,000 אמות or less
away, they could start שבת in the midpoint between the two villages.
They would be able to go the next day from their village
to that midpoint and from that midpoint to the next city. So
rather than put bread out there, they went and they waited till
it got dark and they started there, and then they went home,
and then שבת morning they came. So again this is a case
about the מערב ברגל, m'arev baregel, doing it with your physical presence
and doing it not in some far away place but in a
place you are physically present. Now the irony here is is that
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, is presumably bringing this as evidence that even
for an עשיר ashir you're allowed to do it in person. But
who's an עשיר ashir, here? These are people that are coming to
get handouts. So that's again why רש"י Rashi underscores that עשיר here
means it's really means starting from home as opposed to being caught
being caught on the way. So that was his evidence. Presumably רבי
מאיר might say back that's called an עני, I don't know. But
anyway here you see רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says look, you see,
they did it. They did it without using any bread even though
they started from home. Okay. אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, מתניתין
דייקא, matnitin deika, our משנה Mishnah. also a close read of our
משנה proves like רב נחמן's Rav Nachman read, that they're debating the
case of where you're actually
standing. דתניא, De-tanya, the משנה says, מי שיצא לילך לעיר שמערבין לה
והחזירו חבירו, mi sheyatza leilech l'ir shem'arvin lah v'hecheziro chaveiro, this is
a later משנה, not the משנה we read. Somebody went out to
go to a city that they had an עירוב, והחזירו חבירו, v'hecheziro
chaveiro, and his friend turned him back. His friend said you know
it's hot
today, whatever, you should go home, don't bother going. Okay. So meaning
so where were we?
והחזירו חבירו, v'hecheziro chaveiro, הוא מותר לילך וכל בני העיר אסורין. hu
mutar leilech v'chol b'nei ha'ir asurin. He can go to the city
on שבת, but nobody else can. דברי רבי יהודה. Divrei Rabbi Yehuda.
That's what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says. Now what the heck does
that mean? So the גמרא says, רבינא Ravina posed this, מאי שנא
איהו ומאי שנא אינהו? mai shna ihu u'mai shna inhu? Why? So
apparently he was out Friday afternoon right before it got dark, he
was outside the city, and he was maybe planning on not he
was actually planning on going to city B, he starts in city
A, he was planning on going to city B to spend שבת
there. Okay. And he got halfway and somebody said you know what,
better you should go home, it's getting cold, it's getting dark. He
turned around, he went home. Okay. Next morning שבת morning he can
go to city B but nobody else can. What's going on? What
did he do and why does it work for him and it
doesn't work for other people? So the גמרא says, מאי שנא איהו
ומאי שנא אינהו? mai shna ihu u'mai shna inhu? What's the difference?
אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha bemai askinan,
here we are dealing with שיש לו שני בתים. sheyesh lo shnei
batim. He has two houses. ושני תחומי שבת ביניהם, u'shnei t-chumei Shabbat
beinehem, and you know and the two תחומין of שבת are between
them. Meaning city A, he has a house in city A, he
has a house in city B. Okay. And they're 4,000 or less
אמות between them. איהו, Ihu, he, כיון דנפקא ליה לאורחא, keivan d'nafka
lei l'orchah, when he left Friday afternoon, he was planning on spending
שבת in city B. הוה ליה עני. Hava lei ani. So he
was now effectively, he wasn't going out to place an עירוב, he
was going because he was planning on going to city B. So
he's a guy that's no longer considered at home. He's a guy
that's in the middle of a trip. He's in the middle of
a trip. And therefore, so here he was, right there's his two
homes. Okay. Right? And here he is, he's walking, he's planning on
spending שבת in city B. He gets to midpoint and somebody says
you know what, it's too cold, go home now. So he says
all right, whatever. He turns around and he goes back to city
A. But when he's out on his trip, he's not going out
to place an עירוב, he's going out to go to B. So
he's a guy that's considered to be homeless for the time being,
right? He's not starting from home, he's out on a trip. So
therefore, since he was physically present here when it got dark, that
worked for him as an עירוב. And therefore he can go from
here, right, to the other place. Whereas for the people in the
city, they would need to use bread because if they wanted, they're
effectively starting from home and they would need to use bread. So
okay. So the גמרא
says, הוה ליה עני והנך עשירים נינהו. hava lei ani v'hanach ashirim
ninhu. אלמא כל במקום פלוני עני אין עשיר לא. Alma kol bimkom
ploni ani in ashir lo. Now what the גמרא assumes is though
is that he now again, if this isn't clear either, but so
it's funny that it says that it's inferable from the משנה, but
it assumes that before
Okay, so therefore the גמרא—meaning, let me take a step back. Here's
the issue. Okay, so we have this weird משנה that says it
works for him and not for others. The way we've explained the
difference of the משנה, why can it work for him and not
for others, is he's considered to be a guy outside the home,
and therefore he has more leniencies than the people of his city
that are people in their homes. But one minute, this whole משנה
is, it says דברי רבי יהודה. divrei Rabbi Yehuda. Now רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says that the עירוב ברגליו eiruv b'raglav works whether for
an עני or for an עשיר, right? That was our משנה. רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said I don't care עני or an עשיר. So
here, why would רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, have more leniencies by a
guy that's caught outside the house? If for רבי מאיר—רבי יהודה, an
עני and an עשיר are the same. So the גמרא says, ah,
you see, there must be a case that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says only works for an עני and doesn't work for an עשיר.
And what would that case be? That would be the case where
you're trying to designate a distant spot. If you want שבת to
begin where you are, that's where רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says an
עני or an עשיר. So if this case is a special case
because you're caught outside the home, see, what is the only case
that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda admits is a special case and only
works for an עני? If you're trying to designate a distant spot.
So there you see from this that there is a case that
for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would be limited to an עני, and
that's the case of a distant spot. Okay, so now the גמרא
wraps this up and it says איהו כיוון דנפיק ליה אורחא הוי
ליה עני והנך חשיבי נינהו. Ihu keivan d'nafik lei orcha havi lei
ani vehanach chashivei ninhu. שמע מינה. Shema mina. Wait a minute. איהו
כיוון דנפיק ליה אורחא
הוי ליה עני
והנך
חשיבי נינהו. אלמא, Ihu keivan d'nafik lei orcha havi lei ani vehanach
chashivei ninhu. Alma, so you see there's a distinction between an עני
and an עשיר according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, although רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda. normally denies that distinction. So what is the difference? It
must be כל במקום פלוני עני אין עשיר לא. kol bimakom ploni
ani in ashir lo. The difference must be that this is a
case where you're saying a distant spot. And when it's a distant
spot that you want to designate, that's where רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda.
says—there רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda? would agree: only an עני, not an
עשיר. שמע מינה, Shema mina, that is a good point. So now
the גמרא just ends this: מתני לה רב חייא בר אשי לחייא
בר רב קמיה דרב Masni lah Rav Chiya bar Ashi l'Chiya bar
Rav kamei d'Rav אחד עני ואחד עשיר. So whether the position of
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that said whether an עני or an עשיר
you can do עירוב ברגליו, eiruv b'raglav, ואמר ליה רב: v'amar lei
Rav: סיים בה נמי הלכה כרבי יהודה. Sayeim bah nami halacha k'Rabbi
Yehuda. Right, that's good, and you should teach that as the position
of רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda and you should add to it that
we rule like רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda
Okay, so we
rule like רבי
יהודה. But again, based on the emphasis of the גמרא, only
when you're physically present. To designate a faraway space, that would be
a special exception to a guy that is stuck.
רבה בר בר חנה הוה רגיל דאתי מארתיבנא לפומבדיתא. Rabbah bar bar
Chana hava ragil d'ati m'Artivna l'Pumbedita. He would usually on שבת come
from ארתיבנא Artivna to פומבדיתא, Pumbedita, and that would require making the
special עירובי תחומין. eiruvi techumin. אמר, and he would say, he would
sit at home and say: תהא שביתתי בצינצא. Tehei shvisasi b'Tzinza.
My שבת will be over there in צינצא. Tzinza. צינצא Tzinza was
some particular space. So he did the easy thing, right? He stayed
at home on his easy chair and designated a distant spot. So
אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye said, how do
you think you can get away with that? מאי דעתך? mai datchach?
What are you thinking? רבי מאיר ורבי יהודה הלכה כרבי יהודה? Rabbi
Meir v'Rabbi Yehuda halacha k'Rabbi Yehuda? That we rule like רבי יהודה?
And רב חסדא Rav Chisda says, ואמר רב חסדא, v'amar Rav Chisda,
מחלוקת במקום פלוני, machlokes bimakom ploni,
that רבי יהודה allows an עשיר, even somebody at home, to designate
a faraway space. So that's why you're allowing it? You think we'll
combine רבי יהודה with רב חסדא's Rav Chisda interpretation that you can
designate a faraway space? One minute, והא רב נחמן? v'ha Rav Nachman?
First of all, רב נחמן disagrees and says that when it comes
to a faraway space, everybody agrees it's only for the guy who's
stuck outside.
ותניא כוותיה, v'tanya k'vosei, and we have a ברייתא we just said
a minute ago that showed רב נחמן was right. דתניא כוותיה. d'tanya
k'vosei. That their whole debate is when you are stuck is when
you want to be where you're physically present. To designate a faraway
space, you have to really be an עני, you have to really
be stuck. אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said back to him, הדר
בי, hadar bi, fine, I retract it. Now you've made me have
to schlep out every Friday, fine. אמר רמי בר חמא, Amar Rami
bar Chama, הרי אמרו שבת יש לו ארבע אמות. harei amru Shabbos
yesh lo arba amos. So let's just get to the משנה. שבת
יש לו ארבע אמות. Shabbos yesh lo arba amos.
So they say, you know, we'll end here. It's 8:30. Okay, so
we'll finish this up tomorrow. The upshot of all of this is
is that we had some fascinating issues that you draw a square,
a four by four, 2000 by 2000, which means A, it's going
to be very relevant for תחומין, but number two, what it's also
going to mean is that everything we thought about carrying ארבע אמות,
arba amos. according to one approach, always means carrying 5.6 אמות. According
to another, it depends which direction you're going, which makes a lot
of sense, especially if you conceptualize it as the space of the
object. Carrying out of its space, but out of its space is
a square, so sometimes it's longer than ארבע אמות. Also the idea
of רשות היחיד reshus hayachid might not be, you know, might
not be four by four, it might be
a four by four to the corners of
the compass, or it might be 5.6. Where the גמרא ends by
saying that the whole debate is when you actually are physically present.
רבי מאיר says you need bread and רבי יהודה says you can
be where you are, which makes a lot of sense. Obviously, if
that's where you are, you can start שבת, but if you want
to designate a faraway space, that everybody would agree is a special
exception for the guy stuck outside the city. And that's how the
גמרא ended with this attempt to sort of do it from your
easy chair at home, designate a faraway space, and the גמרא rejected
that, said no, that everybody agrees you have to be the עני
stuck outside, and that was a special exemption that they gave. Okay,
let's look at today's.